你好,学生
hello students
欢迎来到PWN学院的另一个模块
and welcome to another module of pwn college
今天我们将讨论竞争条件
today we're going to be talking about race conditions
竞争条件与时间息息相关
race conditions are deeply grounded in the concept of time
所以我们先聊一下时间
so first let's talk about time
正如阿尔伯特·爱因斯坦所说
as Albert Einstein put it
时间是一个维度
time is basically a dimension
我们可以在该维度间隔布置事件
across which we can lay out events to separate them temporarily
结合个人经历来说
right if you think about time in terms of your own personal experience
以这门课为例
taking this class for example
睡醒
you might wake up.
吃饭
you might eat
学习pwn学院的课程
work on pwn college
吃饭。学习。吃饭。学习。睡觉
eat. work on pwn college. eat. work on pwn college. sleep
他们相邻分布在时间轴上
and this is separated along the axis of time right
这是我们人类的经历
so that's your human experience
进程也有类似的经历
a process has a similar experience
进程执行操作
a process executes operations
按顺序执行操作
performs operations in order
它会初始化
it'll initialize
检查用户输入
then it might look at the input it's received
处理用户输入
it might carry out some action on it
检查接下来的输入
look at the next amount of input
执行更多的操作等等
carry out more actions and so forth
到这里还没问题
this all makes sense
如果有2个进程呢
now what about two processes
假设这个程序启动两次
let's say you launch this program twice
初始化。检查输入。处理。检查输入。处理。等等......
that initializes. checks input. does stuff. checks input. does stuff. and so on
在单个进程内部，都是有序的
to each process they're internally ordered
这没问题，
and this makes sense but in reality
但实际上2个进程运行在一个时间轴
these two processes they execute in a single timeline
在现实世界中，它们必然是交错的
right in the real world and so they are necessarily interleave
他们都会初始化
they get initialized
不在同一个时间
not at exactly the same time
一个肯定会在另一个之前初始化
but one of them will get initialized before the other
一个可能会在另一个进程前检查输入
one of them might check the environment input before the other and so on
它们不会同步执行
they don't all execute exactly simultaneously
即使你同时启动它们
even if you launch them at the same time
为什么会这样?
why is this
这是因为过去的cpu只有1核
in the old days this is because computers had a single CPU
一次只能做一件事
right so you would have one processor that could do one thing at a time
即使在多进程系统中
even on the multi process system
处理器执行一个进程的操作后
that processor would basically carry out the actions of one process
会切换到另一个进程，以此类推
then it would switch to another and so on
现在我们有多核心，
nowadays we have multiple cores but this
某种程度上缓解了问题
kind of alleviates the issue
它提高了一定的并发性
it helps things run more concurrently
但还是有这个问题，例如
but we still have for example
运行的进程比核还多
more processes running on our machines than cores that can execute instructions
这时内核还是要决定
right so the kernel will still decide
安排什么时间执行什么进程
what to schedule at what points
运行的进程还是会被打断交错在一起
your processes as they run will still get interleave
除了cpu之外
aside from CPUs
其它硬件
the other parts of the hardware architecture
也限制了程序的运行
on which your program's run are also limited
内存控制器，取决于内存类型，
memory controllers depending on the type of memory etc
可以实现一些并发写
can maybe handle several concurrent writes
但不是很多
but not very many
也许在高端机器上能达到 4
maybe in a high end workstation 4
硬盘也限制了并发性
your storage media is limited
SSD可以处理一定数量的伪并发写
an SSD can handle some amount of kind of pseudo concurrent writes
但是也不是很多
but again not many
网络
networks you know
在网络连接中，数据包是按顺序发送的
on a network connection packets are sent in order
这是无法回避的
and there's just no getting around that
电缆中，一个时刻只有一个数据
it's a cable that has one packet going cross at a time
或者Wi - Fi信号
or a Wi Fi signal that's
基本相同
basically the same
所以原则上
so the bottom line is that
瓶颈在于底层计算架构
bottlenecks in the architecture underpinning our computing frameworks
我们的底层计算机制
our computing substrate
只能实现部分并发
basically requires these concurrent events to at least be partially serialized
好的
right
让我们来看看这意味着什么
so let's take a look at the implications of this
这是很可拍的
the implication of this are kind of dire right
因为它基本上意味着除非你的程序
because it basically means that unless your program
或两个或更多程序
or two programs or whatever
声明了有对执行顺序的强制要求
have explicit dependencies on order of operation that they enforce
那么，执行顺序只能在单个进程中得到保证
then that execution order can will only be guaranteed within a single process
实际上是在单个线程中
in reality actually this is within a single thread
在要讨论的现实中
and in reality reality as we'll discuss
即使在线程中，也有棘手的极端情况
even within a thread there are corner cases that are pretty tricky
并且会导致很多bug
and can lead to a lot of bugs
比如
so for example
我们看一下
let's look at some possible execution orders  for
同时启动2个进程，它们可能的执行顺序
simultaneous launches of the two processes we've been talking about
1是完美的交错在一起
one order is this perfect interleaving
可能发生，但概率不大
it could happen. it likely won't happen
一般会比这个乱
likely there would be some messy interleaving
但是你可以看到
but you can see
每个进程的单个动作
the individual actions of every process
在进程中是有序的
within that process are ordered
在进程间是没有保证的
between the processes there's no guarantee
可能你启动P1和P2后
so you might launch P1 and P2
它们的动作完美的交织在一起
and have their actions interleave perfectly
也可能启动后
you might launch them
内核让P1先执行完
and have P1 get scheduled by the kernel run all the way through
然后内核再让P2执行完
and then P2 get scheduled by the kernel run all the way through
也可能先执行了部分P1
you might have part of P1 run
然后P2执行完，最后执行剩下的P1
then all of P2 then the rest of P1
还可能P1执行一部分，P2执行一部分
you might have part of P1 part of P2
然后P1执行完，P2再执行完，等等
then the rest of P1 then the rest of P2 and so on right
为什么这是一个问题
why is this a problem
这是个问题，因为
well this is a problem because
有些交错的执行顺序可能会导致bug
certain execution interleavings can be buggy
在这种情况下想象一下
in this case imagine
假如 P1 在 check_input 里检查了关键信息
if P1 make some assumptions or check some critical information in the check input function
然后 P2 也检查了这个关键信息
then P2 does the same thing on an unchanged environment
所以P1和P2检查了相同的环境
so P1 and P2 checked the same environment
检查的可能是文件所属用户之类的
they might look at ownership of files etc etc
然后P1进行一些操作
and then P1 carries out some action
现在环境变了
the environment has now changed
到P2执行操作了
but P2 is carrying out an action
但它的判断是基于环境改动前做的
based on the environment that it checked before P1 changed that environment
这被称为校验时间和使用时间不一致错误
this is called a time of check time of use bug
好的
right
P2执行的操作
this action that P2 is taken
可能不再合法
might no longer be valid
不再安全了
might no longer be safe
因为P1对程序状态进行了更改
because of changes that P1 carried out to the program state
我们等一下看一个例子
we're going to look at an example in just a second
当然，如果不交叉在一起
of course if you don't interleave them
正好是P1执行完再执行P2
they happen to get scheduled one after the other
在这种情况下，不会发生错误
in this case no bug occurs
其他交错类型有其他问题
other interleaving types have other issues
这个
this one
P1和P2完成检查，P2执行多次操作后，P1再do_action
p1's do_action gets run after P2 does the check and action multiple times
P2可能会大量改动环境
this could be massive changes to the environment potentially
但和执行1次操作同理
but conceptually the same as one action
幻灯片最右边，有个有趣的例子
here's an interesting one all the way to the right of the slide
这里有两个问题
here we have two problems
一是P1的do_action在P2之后运行，呃
one is that P1's do_action gets run after P2's
P1先检查输入
P1 checks its input
然后P2改变了环境
then the environment gets changed by P2
然后P1再do_action
and then P1 does its action
但对P2来说也同样有问题
but the opposite is also true
P2第二次检查它的输入
P2 checks its input the second time around
就在P1第一次do_action之前
right before P1 does its first action
这可能会撤销P2之前执行的操作
which might undo actions carried out by P2 previously
然后P2 do_action
and then P2 does its action
取决于程序逻辑
depending on the program logic
这里什么都有可能发生
anything could happen here
我们来看一个例子
so let's take a look at one example
我创建了一个漏洞程序
all right I created a vulnerable application for you
这个漏洞程序
and this vulnerable application
有check_input函数和do_action函数
has a check_input function and a do_action function
check_input函数读取命令行参数指定的文件
the check input function reads a provided file name on the command line
确保文件里的值为0
and make sure that the value in that file name is 0
do_action会读入那个值
and the do_action will read in that value
然后加1，保存到文件
increment it and write it back out
好的
right
如果我问往文件写入0
so if we put in 0 to this file
然后
and then
用该文件执行漏洞程序
we run this on the file
程序告诉我们写入了1，确实写入了1
tells us it wrote a 1 and it indeed wrote a 1
如果再次运行
and then if we run it again
断言失败，并且不会增加
this assertion fails and it won't incremented
好吧
all right
这可以用来表示认证标识，或者权限等级
you can imagine an authenticated or a privilege level
保存的一个递增数字
a number being incremented and stored
好吧
alright
目前看起来很正常
so this seems pretty good right
有趣的是
well interestingly
如果我们重复运行这个
if we run this on repeat let's say
这是一个shell脚本，它将持续执行这个程序
this is a shell script that'll just keep running this
好的
all right
我们把错误告警去掉
let's get rid of the errors
现在我们在重复执行这个漏洞程序
so now we're running this on repeat
在另一个窗口中，如果我们输出num文件
so here in a different window if we cat out the num file
是1
it's 1
如果我们写入0，然后输出
if we write 0 to it and we cat it out again
还是1
it's 1 as well
好的
alright
它告诉我们写入了1
so it tells us it wrote to one
现在
now
会出什么问题?
what could go wrong
会出问题的是
obviously what could go wrong is
如果check_input执行时
if this check input runs
文件中是0
the file has a zero in it
然后在check input和do_action之间
and between check input and do_action
我们在另一个进程中往文件写入1
we open that file and we write a 1 right in a different process
让我们试一试
let's give that a try
我们在这里执行一个循环
so we're gonna do another loop here
持续写入0
we're gonna write 0 here
现在漏洞程序一直在执行并写入1
so this guy is now constantly running and writing ones
它打开文件、读入0，然后写入1
okay so it'll open that file read into 0 and write the 1
在另一个进程中
and then in another process
在另一个窗口中，我们持续往文件中写入1
in another window we're gonna loop and write a 1 to it
为什么我们要往文件里写入1
why are we writing a 1 here
因为我们希望触发
because what we're hoping to trigger
0写入循环写入0
is the loop that's writing a zero will write the zero
然后check_input
then check_input will run
因为这都是多进程运行的
because this is all running multi-process
所以内核会让他们交叉执行
so it can be interleaved by the kernel
然而
however
内核会根据进程优先级来排列
the kernel wants to interleave it based on its internal priorities
不管怎样，写入了一个0
so anyways we write a 0
然后运行check_input
then check_input gets run
检查通过，然后我们又写入了一个1
this check passes and then we write a 1
再执行do_action
and do_action gets run
它读入文件并加1
and it reads in the file and increments it
最后写入了一个2
and ends up writing a 2
0写入循环在执行
so we have our 0 loop is running
1写入循环也在执行
our 1 loop is running
能时不时看到 wrote 2!
and you can see wrote 2 is blinking by
如果现在关闭漏洞程序
if you just kill it
已经写入了几次2了
several times we wrote a 2
好的
alright
有趣的是
interestingly
这显然违反了程序的初衷
so this is obviously a violation of the intent of the program
很明显，程序的目的只是写入1
the program is very clearly written with the intent of only writing a 1
因为这个检查确保里面的文件是0
because this check make sure that the file in there was a 0
这是一个有趣的例子，
alright this is an interesting example also because
还因为它能和自己竞争条件
it has a race condition to against itself
如果在两个循环中执行这个程序
so if you run two of these in a loop
最终
then eventually
我们会遇到这样的情况
we'll get a situation where
它们都执行了check_input
they'll each do a check_input
他们看到文件内是0
they'll see that the file is 0
然后打开文件并增加它
and then one will open the file and increment it
让它变成1
making it 1
然后另一个进程会打开这个文件
and then the next one will open the file increment that
让它变成2
making it 2
让我们来看看这是如何工作的
let's take a look at how this will work
我们在一个循环中执行它
so we run this in one
先关闭其他循环。都关了
let's kill the other loops. they're killed
好的，我们在一个循环中执行它
okay we run this in a loop
我们在另一个循环中执行它
we run a second iteration of it in the loop
好的
ok
boom
所以
so
这个循环写入了1
this guy wrote a 1
这个循环检测到1退出了，什么也没写
and this guy errored out didn't write anything
我们在这个循环持续重置为0
let's just keep resetting this in a loop
最终我们会看到写入2
eventually we'll see someone writing a two
好的
and I think yes
写入了2。很酷吧
wrote two. pretty cool huh
好吧
all right
这是在同一个程序的不同进程中的竞争条件
so that's a race condition just between two iterations of the same program
所以有可能同一个漏洞程序的不同进程互相竞争
so it can be two iterations of vulnerable program racing against each other
通常是一个漏洞程序进程的不同线程之间竞争
oftentimes it is going to be two iterations two different threads in a vulnerable program
我们马上会讲到这个
we'll talk about that in a second
有时漏洞程序的竞争对象是
sometimes it is one program racing against you
你在命令行启动的其它进程
on the command line doing other stuff in a different process
好的
all right
我们如何利用这个漏洞呢
so how do we exploit this
一般情况下
right the general case
当发现这种危险并发
you identify this unsafe concurrency
你要找出应该在哪里插入操作
you figure out where you need to inject an action
要想办法让这个插入点尽可能大
you figure out how to make this point as big as possible
增加修改中间状态的几率
had to make increase your chances of changing the state between
就是在进程检查状态后
the time where the program verifies it
和本应该执行的操作之前
and the time where the program actually does whatever action it wants to do
修改进程状态
and then you very carefully modify that state
让程序接下来的操作
so that the action that the program is taking
对攻击者有利
end up being in your benefit and the attacker's benefit
在本模块后续章节中
through the rest of the module
我们会讨论你该怎么做
we'll talk about how you'll do this and
并讨论如何保护
talk about how you would protect software against these sort of problems
快速过一下竞争条件的历史
all right real quick note about the history of race conditions
我喜欢加入一些历史
I always try to include a little bit of history
加入一些问题的历史背景
a little bit of historical context for all these problems
竞争条件是一个比较古老的概念
race conditions were our pretty old concept
最初是在硬件背景中讨论这个问题
originally they were discussed in a hardware context
有
you have
通过导线连接的逻辑门
logic gates connected by wires
它们之间有信号流动
and there are signals flowing between them
这时的竞争条件是
and the race condition was literally
不同信号分别在不同导线上竞争
a signal racing against another signal along two different wires
许多人探索过这个问题
these were explored by a number of people
包括大卫·霍夫曼，他最出名的作品是霍夫曼编码
including David Huffman who is probably most famous for Huffman encoding
但除了霍夫曼编码
but aside from Huffman encoding
他还
he also
写了一篇完整的博士论文
wrote an entire PhD thesis
包含了对竞争条件的大量研究
that included a lot of work on race conditions
并讨论了安全相关或bug导致的竞争条件
and discussion of security critical  or buggy bug inducing race conditions
相对于安全的竞争条件(的差异)等
versus safe race conditions etc
这是在1954年出的论文
all the way back to 1954
这是一个非常古老的话题，有60多年的历史了
so this is a very ancient topic over 60 years old
通过这个模块
and through this module you're gonna get
你对它的熟悉程度将远远超过霍夫曼
way more familiar with it than Hoffman ever had a chance to
好运
good luck